Guide to the Clarence Day Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Clarence Day collection
1891-1963
YCAL MSS 583
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3
(8 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, and printed material documenting the career of Clarence Shepard Day. The collection provides insight into Day's work as an author, illustrator, and humorist, who often poked fun at upper class New Yorkers. The collection also documents Day's experience as an undergraduate student at Yale University in the late nineteenth-century. Correspondents include: Alfred A. Knopf and Vira Whitehouse.
Day, Clarence, 1874-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources, 1939-1995. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Clarence Day (1874-1935)
Clarence Shepard Day, Jr., American author, illustrator, and humorist, was born in New York City to Clarence Shepard and Lavinia Elizabeth Stockwell Day on November 18, 1874.
Day graduated from Yale University in 1896 with a Bachelor of Arts. After graduation Day worked as a stockbroker in his father's company. He trained with the U.S. Navy during the Spanish-American War, serving on the Nahant, which remained in the New York Harbor. Day suffered from arthritis, which forced him to leave the military and eventually to end his career as a stockbroker.
Day's illness prompted him to begin a career as a freelance writer and illustrator. He was the owner and publisher of the Yale Alumni Weekly (1905-1909), published pieces in Harper's, New Yorker, Saturday Evening Post, Yale Review, and New Republic, and completed freelance work for other authors. Day also wrote book reviews and a financial column for the Metropolitan Magazine under the pseudonym B. H. Arkwright (1915-1921).
Day's books include: This Simian World (1920), The Crow's Nest (1921), Thoughts without Words (1928), God and My Father (1932), In the Green Mountain Country (1934), Scenes from the Mesozoic (1935), Life with Father (1935), After All (a revision of The Crow's Nest, 1936), and Life with Mother (1937). Life with Father was a bestseller in 1935 and 1936 and was a Book-of-the-Month Club selection. The book was also adapted for theatre, film, and television.
Day married Katherine Briggs Dodge in 1928 with whom he had one daughter (Wendy Day). Day died at his home in New York City of pneumonia on December 28, 1935.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, and printed material documenting the career of Clarence Shepard Day. The collection provides insight into Day's work as an author, illustrator, and humorist, who often poked fun at upper class New Yorkers. The collection also documents Day's experience as an undergraduate student at Yale University in the late nineteenth-century.
Day's creative life is represented in his correspondence with publisher Alfred A. Knopf, as well as in his illustrated letters to friends including Albert Galloway Keller, Mary Thompson, and Vira Whitehouse. Drafts for Scenes from the Mesozoic reflect Day's work as an author and humorist. The collection does not include extensive documents pertaining to Day's most well-known publication, Life With Father, but the Writings and Artwork Series does include letters relating to a publicity stunt in order to promote the book in Chicago. The Writings and Artwork series also represents Day's career as an author and illustrator, including his freelance illustrations for Florence Guy Seabury's The Delicatessen Husband and Lee Wilson Dodd's Pegeen and the Potamus. Some of Day's shorter pieces, such as poetry and short stories, are included in the Printed Material series.
Day's involvement with Yale University, as a student and an alumnus, are traced in his scrapbook dating from 1895 to 1897, correspondence with classmate Albert Galloway Keller, and illustrations for various alumni events from 1909 to 1960.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1892-1963. II. Writings and Artwork, 1891-1980. III. Personal Papers, 1895-1960. IV. Printed Material, 1924-1936.
American literature -- 20th Century; Day, Clarence, 1874-1935; Whitehouse, Vira Boarman, 1875-1957; Alfred A. Knopf, Inc
- Correspondence, 1892-1963; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents the professional and personal life of Clarence Day (including works published posthumously) between 1892 and 1963. Most notably Day's correspondence with the Alfred A. Knopf company provides insight into his career as a writer and illustrator. The series contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence; Day frequently illustrated his correspondence with friends and family, including his letters to Yale University classmate Albert Galloway Keller, Mary Thompson, and Vira Whitehouse.
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. to Clarence Day, 1921-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
    Includes correspondence with Alfred A. Knopf, Alfred William Koshland, Basil N. Bass, Stimson and a photograph of Clarence and Peg Day
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. from Clarence and Peg Day, 1921-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9-16)
  - Adams, J. C., letter from Clarence Day (photostat), 1908 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Day, George Parmly, letters from Clarence Day, 1892-1908 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes 2 letters and 1 original pencil drawing
  - Donaldson, Norman, letters from Clarence Day, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Donaldson, Norman, letters concerning Clarence Day, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fuller, Clement Austin, letters from Clarence Day, 1912-1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Includes 3 drawings with notes
  - Gibney, Virgil Pendleton, 1905-1915 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Goldenbook Magazine, letter to Clarence Day, 1934 November 17 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Hawley, Margaret Foote, letters from Clarence Day, 1919-1925 (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
  - Hawley, Margaret Foote, letters to Clarence Day, 1920-1923 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hawley, Margaret Foote, letters to Geoffrey Parsons, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hawley, Margaret Foote, obituary, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Johnson, Alvin, letter to Clarence Day, 1935 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Johnson, Frederic Blair, letters from Clarence Day, 1906-1924 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Includes 10 letters from Clarence Day and 2 letters from George Parmly Day to Yale University concerning the letters
  - Keller, Albert Galloway, 1903-1935 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Contains 2 bound volumes of copies of correspondence from Clarence Day to Albert G. Keller
  - Keller, Carl T., letters from Clarence Day, 1919-1921 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Keogh, Andrew, 1916-1935 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Lewis, Wilmarth Sheldon, letters from Clarence Day, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Includes 5 letters with envelopes, original pen and ink drawing, and reproduction of a drawing
  - MCA Management, 1947 June 5 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Oakley, Louis C., letters from Clarence Day, 1904-1918 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Includes 11 illustrated notes
  - Thompson, Mary, letters from Clarence Day, 1903-1905 (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
  - Thompson, Mary, letters from Clarence Day, 1906-1935 (Box 3, Folder 42-43)
  - Welch, Lewis S., 1914 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Includes 2 letters with drawings from Clarence Day and copies of his replies
  - Whitehouse, Vira, from Clarence Day, 1918-1920 (Box 3, Folder 45-49)
  - Whitehouse, Vira, from Clarence Day, 1920-1935 (Box 4, Folder 50-59)
    Includes drafts of untitled poems, short stories, and a copy of Max
  - Various correspondents, including copyright agreement, 1921-1939 (Box 4, Folder 60)
- Writings and Artwork, 1891-1980; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  This series documents Clarence Day's career as an author and illustrator, mostly relating to his freelance illustrations for Florence Guy Seabury's The Delicatessen Husband and Lee Wilson Dodd's Pegeen and the Potamus. The series includes Day's work on his book Scenes from the Mesozoic and some early drawings. Some publicity for Life With Father is also in the series, most notably correspondence relating to Alfred A. Knopf's offer of fifty dollars for the best letter explaining why the book did not sell well in Chicago.
  - The Delicatessen Husband, original illustrations for Florence Guy Seabury's book, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 61-62)
    Includes a copy of the printed version
  - Life with Father
    - Third-party letters to Alfred A. Knopf in response to his offer of $50 for the best letter on the reason why Day's Life with Father did not sell well in Chicago, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 63-65)
    - Clipping about Life With Father and typescript memoir (possibly by Alfred A. Knopf) about publishing the book, 1948, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - "Noble Boys," printed version, The Saturday Review, 1936 November 14 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Pegeen and the Potamus, original pen and ink drawing by Clarence Day for Lee Wilson Dodd's book, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - "To Phoebe," typescript and autograph manuscript of poem, 1909, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    Includes a letter about the poem from George Parmly Day (1946)
  - Scenes from the Mesozoic, typescript, illustrations, original pencil sketches, production file, memos, proofs, and notes, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 70-71)
  - Early pen and ink sketch by Clarence Day, 1891, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    Includes letter of authentication from George Parmly Day (1947)
  - Drawings signed and mounted, 10 pencil drawings and 4 ink drawings, undated
- Personal Papers, 1895-1960; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series contains material relating to Clarence Day's affiliation with Yale University as both a student and an alumnus.
  - Scrapbook of Yale College and New Haven memorabilia, 1895-1897
  - Class of 1896, 1909-1960 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    Includes printed circulars, menus, postal cards, etc. regarding reunion of the Class of 1896, Yale College
- Printed Material, 1924-1936; Series IV; 3
  The series consists of printed material either by or about Clarence Day. A selection of Day's poetry, short stories, and essays, published between 1924 and 1936 are represented here.
  - Clippings of writings by Clarence Day, 1924-1936 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    "In Woodlawn" (1926), "Life with Mother" (1936), "Father has a Bad Night" (1933), "Father Thumps on the Floor," "Father Feels Starved," "Father Hires a Cook," "Father and the Crusader's Third Wife," "Father is Firm with his Ailments," "Shorten Kiss," and "Father Lets in the Telephone" (1933)
  - Clippings about Clarence Day, undated (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Pamphlets, undated (Box 6, Folder 76)
- Oversize, 0.5; (2 boxes)
  - Scrapbook of Yale College and New Haven memorabilia, 1895-1897 (Box 7, Folder 77-79)
  - Drawings signed and mounted, undated (Box 8, Folder 80)